Guide to the Harry Y. Ueno Papers, 1912-1997
Department of Special Collections
Ueno, Harry Y. (Harry Yoshio), 1907-. Papers,
1912-1997
M0930
Ueno, Harry Y. (Harry Yoshio), 1907-
1.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Papers relating to the Harry Ueno's internment at Camp Manzanar in 1942. Includes correspondence, clippings, and oral history interview.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harry Yoshio Ueno, 1997.
Biography
During World War II, approximately 120,000 Japanese Americans were deemed a national security threat and placed in internment camps. Contrary to common belief, Japanese Americans protested against their involuntary confinement. The Manzanar Riot is among the most renowned examples of internee resistance and Harry Ueno played a central role in it. Harry Ueno was born on April 14, 1907 in Hawaii. When he was eight years old, he was taken to Hiroshima, Japan, to be educated. Afler graduating from the Kuba City grammar school and attending a trade school in Tokyo for nearly a year, he returned to the United States in 1923. He held various positions in Washington and northern California before moving to Los Angeles in 1931. In Los Angeles, he and his wife, Yaso, had three children. Harry Ueno was employed as a salesman for retail fruits and vegetables until the evacuation. The Ueno family was evacuated to Manzanar. A few months into his internment, he initiated the investigation of the sugar and beef shortage, and organized 1,600 kitchen workers into Mess Hall Workers Union. On December 5, 1942, Tayama, a JACL (Japanese American Citizen's League) leader in Manzanar, was severely beaten by masked internees. Although Ueno was arrested for this incident, he was not charged or given a trial. The internees in Manzanar congregated in front of Ueno's jail cell demanding his release. Ueno was the veritable folk hero, the martyr of Manzanar, around whom the internees marched. The riot ended with eight internees wounded and two killed. Ueno along with other camp leaders were removed to isolation centers where they were cut off from all contact. It was not until nearly a year later, that he would see his family again. With the war's end, the Ueno family resettled in northern California and began a cherry and strawberry farm. Harry Ueno is now retired, and is an act!ve member and supporter of the Japanese American community and its related research.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The Harry Ueno Collection consists of 2 linear feet of original and photocopied manuscript materials, newspaper clippings, and photographs. Much of the Japanese-language materials were kept as they were found when the collection first arrived at Stanford University Libraries. However, most of the English-language manuscripts have been rearranged into six series or topics for easier access to materials. The war-time diaries of Harry Ueno, Yaso Ueno, and Masunaka are valuable parts of this collection. Harry Ueno's Japanese language diary have been re-arranged by the organizer in a chronological order. Also unique to this collection, is Ueno's handwritten record and member lists of the Manzanar Mess Hall Union lists found in Box 1. Series 2, containing newspaper clippings, will be especially helpful for scholars working with redress and reparation. Lastly, many of the government documents are missing pages and may be hard to follow.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bendetsen, Karl R.; Hayakawa, S.I. (Samuel Ichiyâe), 1906-; Hohri, William Minoru, 1927-; Kurihara, Joseph Y.; Myer, Dillon S. (Dillon Seymour), 1891-; Ueno, Yasoko.; Welgyn, Michi.; Japanese American Citizens' League.; Japanese American Citizens' League. National Committee for.; National Council for Japanese American Redress.; United States. War Relocation Authority.; Concentration camps--United States.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Evacuation of civilians.; World War, 1939-1945--Japanese Americans.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons, American.; Manzanar (Calif.); Manzanar National Historic Site (Calif.); Manzanar War Relocation Center.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Writings from the Camp and Published Journal Articles
  - Ueno's Diaryn.a. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Handwritten Japanese-languaged documentsn.a. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manzanar Mess Hall Union (member signatures and notes) n.a. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - JACL Manzanar Reportn.a. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Published Journal Articles1977-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 2. Newspaper Clippings
  - Harry Ueno and related articlesn.a. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Jap Evacuees Camp Kit Results in Martial Law"12/7/42 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - World War Il - military1942-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Japanese American soldiersn.a. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Redress and Reparation (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Redress and Reparation (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Editorialn.a. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Editorial1970s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Editorial1980s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Editorial1990s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - JACL (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Internment Experience and Reflections (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal - debates, hearings, bills (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Manzanar (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Moab (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - TuleLake (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Day of Remembrance (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tokyo Rose (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Articles Honoring Individuals (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Internment Related Works and Research (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Japanese American Artists and their works (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tozai Times (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Various newspaper sections (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Japanese-languaged articles (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Vincent Chin (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous articles (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Series 3. Government Documents
  - Ueno, Harry (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kurihara, Joe (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Masaoka, Joe and Mike (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Corn to/from Karl R. Bendetsen1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Corn to/from Dillon S. Myer1943 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jerome5/28/43 "Interview with Reverend Kunishichi Iwori and Reverend Hideo Hashimoto" (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Leupp1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lone Pine Jail12/12/42 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manzanarl942-194A (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manzanar Riot1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Moab (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Topaz (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tule Lake (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dept. of Justice - misc. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - FBI-misc. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - JACL (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Navy Intelligence (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Renunciats (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Unknown Person Report the Manzanar Incident"12/16/42 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - WRA - misc. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series 4. Correspondence
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Clements, Len; Cook, Christopher; Crouch, Tom; Embrey, Sue K.; Eto, Shinkichi; Fugita, Steve; Hayakawa, S. I.; Herzig, Jack and Aiko; Hobri, William; Komuri, Yoshihisa; Lim, Deborah; Lin, Che-Hwei; Machak, Frank; Okihiro, Gary Y.; Omura, James M.; Tateishi, John; Uyeda, Clifford I.; Weglyn, Michi; Yamada, George; Yamasaki, Jennie
  - Correspondence from Harry Ueno to Yasoko Ueno1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from Art Hansen to Harry Ueno1982-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Corr. from Art Hansen, not to Harry Ueno1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Corn from Nakagawa, Mitsuo1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Corr. to/from Tamura, Eileen H.1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Corn not to/from Ueno1972-1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1940s Corr.1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 5. Miscellaneous Writings
  - Writings on/about Harry Ueno (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Manzanar Martyr specific materials (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Yaso(ko) Ueno Diary1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Masunaka Diary1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Ishihara, Shintaro Interview (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Kurihara, Joe Y. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Myer, Dillon (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Weglyn, Michi's commencement speech given at Pomona College (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "A private report on the incident of Dec. 6, 1942" / by Koichi Tsuji (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Draft Resisters (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Fair Practice Committee (Manzanar) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Hayakawa testimony before Subcommittee1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - JACL (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Legal representation of Japanese Americans (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - List of names at Tule Lake1943 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Lone Pine County Jail inmate signatures1943 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous handwritten notes (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - California Journal11/1986 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Epistolarian by William Hohri (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Manzanar Reunion by William Hohri (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Nikkei Heritage1992 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "Segregator" by Richard Drinnon (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Tule Lake Pilgrimage1991 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Leupp (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Manzanar during war time (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Manzanar National Historic Site (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - National Council for Japanese American Redress (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Japanese American Historical Encyclopedia headwords1991 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Informational Flyers and Letters (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - UCLA Archive (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Series 6. Photographs
  - Photographs1912-1997 (Box 4, Folder 39)